<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<module>
  <title>fad</title>
  <meta>length, long, while, for, all, whole, duration</meta>
  <p>
    <strong>fad</strong>
    <en>length</en> is an abstract (masculine) noun, derived from the adjective <strong><a href="?gd=fada">fada</a></strong>
    <en>long</en>.</p>
  <p>Forms of <strong>fad</strong> are also used to introduce a temporal adverbial phrase or clause, as if it were a preposition or conjunction.</p>
  <hr/>
  <p>The main uses of <strong>fad</strong> are –</p>
  <ol>
    <li>As an abstract noun meaning <en>length</en>, the quality of being <en>long</en><boxlink ref="#noun"/>
    </li>
    <li>As a pseudo-preposition, governing a noun denoting a time interval, and introducing a temporal adverbial phrase of <em>duration</em> – <ol type="a">
        <li><em>indefinite</em> – <mark>bha sinn pòsta fad bliadhna</mark>
          <en>we were married for a year</en><boxlink ref="#preposition-indefinite"/></li>
        <li><em>definite</em> – <mark>bha sinn còmhla ri chèile fad na bliadhna</mark>
          <en>we were together all year (long)</en><boxlink ref="#preposition-definite"/></li>
      </ol>
    </li>
    <li>As a pseudo-conjunction <strong>fhad ’s a ...</strong>, governing an imperfective clause, and introducing a temporal adverbial clause of duration – <ol type="a">
        <li>modifying an <em>imperfective</em> – <en>as long as</en>, <en>(all the) while</en>, e.g. <mark>fhad ’s a bha mi thall thairis, bha i ag obair</mark>
          <en>all the while I was abroad, she was working</en><boxlink ref="#conjunction-imperfective"/></li>
        <li>modifying a <em>perfective</em> – <en>while</en>, e.g. <mark>fhad ’s a bha mi thall thairis, phòs i</mark>
          <en>while I was abroad, she got married</en><boxlink ref="#conjunction-perfective"/></li>
      </ol>
    </li>
  </ol>

  <box id="noun">
    <title><mark>fad</mark> as a de-adjectival noun</title>
    <p>The most straightforward use of <strong>fad</strong> is as an abstract noun meaning <en>length</en>, derived from the adjective <strong><a href="?gd=fada">fada</a></strong>
      <en>long</en>. For example –</p>
    <xl>
      <li>2938</li>
    </xl>
  </box>

  <box id="preposition-indefinite">
    <title><mark>fad</mark> as a pseudo-preposition of temporal duration – indefinite uses</title>
    <p><strong>fad</strong> can be used as a kind of preposition introducing a time adverbial phrase describing the duration of a state or activity. When <strong>fad</strong> governs an
        <em>indefinite</em> time interval noun, it means something like English <en>for</en>.</p>
    <xl>
      <li>2950</li>
      <li>2940</li>
      <li>2951</li>
    </xl>
    <p>See the corresponding durative use of <strong><a href="?gd=airson&amp;box=duration">airson</a></strong>
      <en>for</en>.</p>
  </box>

  <box id="preposition-definite">
    <title><mark>fad</mark> as a pseudo-preposition of temporal duration – definite uses</title>
    <p>When the temporal durational pseudo-preposition <strong>fad</strong> governs a <em>definite</em> time interval noun, it corresponds to English <en>all ... (long)</en>, <en>the whole</en>,
        <en>throughout</en>.</p>
    <xl>
      <li>2935</li>
      <li>2949</li>
      <li>2937</li>
    </xl>
  </box>

  <box id="conjunction-imperfective">
    <title><mark>fhad ’s a</mark> as a temporal pseudo-conjunction – imperfective uses</title>
    <p><strong>fad</strong> can be used as a kind of conjunction, introducing an imperfective temporal adverbial clause describing the time period over which some other situation extends, or within
      which an action happens. In this sense, <strong>fad</strong> is usually lenited and conjoined using a contracted version of <strong>agus</strong>
      <en>and</en> with a relative clause, i.e. <strong>fhad ’s a (tha)</strong>.</p>
    <p>When the pseudo-conjunction <strong>fhad ’s a</strong> introduces a temporal adverbial which modifies an <em>imperfective</em> state or activity, it corresponds to the English conjunctions
        <en>as long as</en>, <en>(all the) while</en>. For example –</p>
    <xl>
      <li>2939</li>
      <li>2941</li>
    </xl>
    <p>See also: <strong><a href="?gd=nuair">nuair</a></strong>
      <en>when</en>.</p>
  </box>

  <box id="conjunction-perfective">
    <title><mark>fhad’s a</mark> as a temporal pseudo-conjunction – perfective uses</title>
    <p>When the pseudo-conjunction <strong>fhad ’s a</strong> introduces a temporal adverbial which modifies a <em>perfective</em> action or event, it corresponds to the English conjunction 
      <en>while</en>. For example –</p>
    <xl>
      <li>2943</li>
      <li>2945</li>
      <li>2948</li>
    </xl>
    <p>See also: <strong><a href="?gd=nuair">nuair</a></strong> <en>when</en>.</p>
  </box>

</module>
