<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../../module.rnc" schematypens="https://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0?>
<module>
  <title>proper nouns</title>
  <p>Proper nouns are <a href="?xx=nouns/nouns">nouns</a> which are also <a href="?xx=nouns/names">names</a>, 
    identifying and referring to a single entity – a specific person, animal, place, organisation &amp;c.</p>
  <p>Like all nouns, proper nouns have a <u>gender</u> – they are either feminine or masculine –</p>
  <ul>
    <li><m>Mairead</m>
      <en>Margaret</en> and <m>Sasainn</m>
      <en>England</en> are examples of feminine proper nouns.</li>
    <li><m>Seumas</m>
      <en>James</en> and <m>Bòd</m>
      <en>Bute</en> are example of masculine proper nouns.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Since they refer to single entities, all proper nouns are singular. There are no plural proper nouns.</p>
  <p>Like all nouns, proper nouns are declined for <u>case</u> – they can have nominative, dative and genitive forms –</p>
  <ul>
    <li>The dative and genitive forms of <i>Mairead</i> are both <m>Maireid</m>.</li>
    <li>The genitive forms of <i>Seumas</i> and <i>Bòd</i> are <m>Sheumais</m> and <m>Bhòid</m> respectively.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Like other nouns, proper nouns can be <u>modified</u> by attributive adjectives, e.g. <m>Seumas Beag</m>
    <en>Little James</en>, <m>Mairead bhàn bhòidheach</m>
    <en>pretty fair Margaret</en>, <m>Sasainn Nuadh</m>
    <en>New England</en>. Capitalisation of the adjective depends on whether it is assumed to be part of the (nick)name of the entity.</p>
  <p>Like all names, proper nouns belong to different semantic classes, depending on the kind of entity they identify –</p>
  <ol>
    <li><a href="?xx=nouns/anthroponymic_proper_nouns">anthroponymic proper nouns</a> name <u>people</u> (including personified entities), 
      e.g. <m>Mairead</m>, <m>Seumas</m>.</li>
    <li><a href="?xx=nouns/toponymic_proper_nouns">toponymic proper nouns</a> name <u>places</u> (geographical entities), e.g. <m>Bòd</m>, <m>Sasainn</m>.</li>
  </ol>
</module>
